welcome to meditating with John ririki
I'm a cognitive psychologist and a
cognitive scientist at the University of
Toronto where I study scientifically
academically mindfulness related
phenomenon like insight flow mystical
experience transformative experience the
cultivation and aspiration towards
wisdom welcome this is a course so if
you're joining us you're welcome to stay
but you should know that every Monday's
is a teaching day a drama day I teach
her new lesson we go through an exercise
and then we incorporate it into our
practice for the rest of the week so
Monday's there's a lesson we sit though
there's QA Tuesdays through Fridays we
meet we sit together and I answer
questions at the end for previous
lessons and sits you'll find it a link
in the description to this video so
today I'm just going to sit and then
we'll have some time for questions at
the end so please turn your phone's your
phones off get your timer ready get your
position
we'll begin what I say begin again
you
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate what you call timidity in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition coming out
of your sit it's always part of your
practice so we have time for a couple
questions one is from Dean ruble I find
my Letta mantra' turns into a sort of
prayer 11 step recovery related then
just fall back into the past now after
those I visualize had dissipated in any
temporal issues with this so the
question I would ask you to Dean is it
is when it becomes a prayer not that
familiar with 12 steps I've dated
somebody at one time and I went to some
meetings I have some sense of it but I
guess the thing I want to know is when
you're into that prayer state is it
doing what the meta is intended to do is
it doing that reciprocal opening are you
moving are you letting go of categorical
identities are you opening up in a
reciprocal fashion like a reciprocal and
couple fashion the mortise within and
the mortise without our use very
basically remembering the being mode if
that's happening then the fact that it's
prayer like is fine there are various
forms of meditation Christian meditation
that overlap with prayer in this manner
so that's what's happening with you
that's fine if after you you've
visualized the people what happens is
you know it sort of dissipates and you
return to the past no that's fine as
well but see once you when you realize
you're back into Posner see you can then
just gently go back out to where you
were in meta and then let it come back
to the past and generally it again and
then back this is a question from the
music group I find while I'm meditating
when mouth fills with saliva or I get to
the ER to swallow is there anything I do
to prevent this that it often becomes a
distraction so just follow as much as
you want for a while
okay just keep swallowing you've built
up the habit that you don't notice that
throughout the day
so you know you've got monkey mind it's
figured out a thing to use to distract
you but throughout the day you're
probably swallowing without noticing so
just let yourself swallow just swallow
swallow a lot all oh and then keep going
back to the breath again and again again
and what you're trying to do is trigger
your deeper long-standing habit of
swallowing throughout the day without
giving you to these special noticing but
the fact that you're sort of trying not
to notice it is making it's alien so you
sort of have to okay befriend it I'll
just swallow you'll take my attention
for a bit I'll label it swallowing ing
and then return to the breath again and
again and again and eventually what will
happen is that will fall away into the
background and a career i watch the net
instructions a few times but I still
only come out as asking three four
questions that feel like not really
getting in yet is it okay to stay with
training the arrow for now yes yes so if
you're getting a strong sense that you
need to keep working on the capacitor
for a while and that needs to get deeper
before you can move it to better that do
that maybe try once a week doing the
meadow and and then try also throughout
the day like you know I recommend it
throughout the day try to catch yourself
and do a one-minute or a few breaths of
pasta maybe you throughout the day just
where you're standing try and do that
reciprocal open trying to remember the
being bow try to open up your sense that
felt sense that there's more to you than
all of your labels and categories and
there's more to everything it's almost
like you've walked into a museum and you
come into that reverential silent or an
art gallery and you're now looking at
things in the being mode and you're
experiencing yourself at be ignored in
relationship to that you can turn any
place you are like that into an art
gallery Milton said this in Paradise
Lost the mind is its own place and can
make a hell out of heaven
and in heaven out of hell so wherever
you are you can sort of do that exercise
to try and strengthen your sense of meta
so I'd like to thank you for joining
today as always I'd like to thank that
my techno mage and your friend Omar my
beloved son Jason for all of their help
please subscribe to the video to be
noticed of the next video you'll also
find on my channel all kinds of you know
videos about insight and flow and the
being mode and modal confusion and
reciprocal opening and the cultivation
of wisdom and but the meeting crisis
itself which is being exacerbated by the
virus crisis that they are in please
invite others to you who might benefit
from this and almost everybody would
please invite others to to this practice
help me to help as many people as I
possibly can we're doing this weekly
mornings at 9:30 est Mondays our Dharma
days teaching days Tuesdays for Fridays
sit day every day and Q&A
see you tomorrow everyone remember
continuity of practice more important
than quantity take care everyone